Today, we continue the reinforcement learning for animation.
And we will be looking at one of my favorite paper
because it influenced the community a lot
and probably led to the motion matching as we know it today.
But also because it's still a lot referenced on research
today because of its way of encoding the animation data
and using the animation data.
Hi, I'm Jerome.
And today's paper is Motion Field for Character Animation,
paper from 2010. So as usual, I will import all my libraries. I've done it before because I have
PyTorch this time, so it takes a bit of time. And then I will load my character. I will load
my little displacement mesh. And I will load a lot of animations, even if I'm not actually using
all of them, I'm taking a few steps in some of them. But I keep loading all of those. And
I will compute the contact to know when the foot is on the ground and I'll do it only by checking the speed of the toes
And that's it. And so that's here all the animation I have
So basically it's all from the LaFan again, so a lot of really long take of locomotions
of different style, but
I'll pick a few of those at the end
So, what the motion field does, it has four concepts that instead of using animations,
we will build a database of motion.
So the way that is composed is basically you have a pose, oops, that's not what I wanted
to do.
You have a pose.
And the pose only represents the position of the character in space and the orientation
of all his bones.
In my case, because I have a root and a hip, so I get the two positions and I get the orientation
of every bones.
And then we also, for all of those poses, you also compute the velocity by doing the
finite difference.
So you take the next frame and you remove your current frame.
And that's give you basically the delta
that will allow you to say, if I'm in this pose
and I add this delta, I will be in the next frame.
And for the motion field, motion state is basically this.
It's one pose and one velocity.
So if one really, if it's one pose
and how much delta you will lead to the next frame.
And that's how you will build the motion states.
will do this for all your frame of animations and you just stores pose and velocities as a big
database. So I will have functions to compute those. Because I will have all my data inside of a
big buffer, I will have a pose pack and unpack functions to easily take a buffer returns structures
as a root, hips and quaternions and then put that back into a buffer because it's a 4D buffers but
you know positions only three 3Ds the quaternions 4Ds and all kind of stuff so I didn't want to
deal too much with that so I just have functions that allow me to read and write inside of the
buffer basically easily. I get the functions that I need to add to a pose together so a pose in a
velocity but really there is no difference between velocities or pose in this case.
So it's just that add functions here and get the subtract function here.
So that's how you to add back the velocity to the positions.
You get the subtract, that's how you do the opposite of course.
Then I get the love to be able to love between two poses and I get the blending that's how you
to take x number of poses with the same number of weights and do the average sum of that pose.
So all that functions that I would need later in the paper to work properly. And then I will have
a function that will allow me to go back into a skeleton and display my results from a pose.
Now, I will build my database with those functions and with a bunch of walking animations
and a bunch of jogging animations, and I will just run this so I have all my states.
And you know, I pick all my positions into, pack all my positions in one buffer, pack
all my velocities in one buffer, then I get the y, it comes also later, is the next frame,
and I get the contacts, so all my contact informations. And see in total I have now
6400 pose states inside of my database, and that's basically 6000 frames of animations.
and I can display those so you can see all of the pose where we set into the
zero-zero position so they're all now relative to the identity so I will
start to be able to work with all of those states and then I can also
display what is the next frame you know so that's my pose plus the next frame
and so you can start to see that that's how we could still remember there is
emotions and that the velocities of the root, the velocity of the heaps, and all
of my orientations. So, but that's all the single states that are inside of my
motion field. Well, my database right now, not the motion field yet. Then what we
will need with this is to be able to compute the similarity matrix. So basically trying
to see how close every pose are from each other and then we will compute the similarity
weight. So you get the distance and then you get really the weights of how close the two
are. And I've used a little different functions that the one I've used in the paper. In the paper
they were only using the orientations of all the bones in the current pose and in the next pose
when they integrated the velocity with it. What I will do is that I will just take the
the character positions of all my bones and I will compute the velocity with the next frames.
So its matrix is a bit different but it works the same way.
So this functions allow me to receive basically a state and a velocity and to turn that into
one vector that I will start to be able to compute different waves.
So I will do this for every states inside of my database.
And then we compute a big matrix with a distance.
So it becomes a matrix of number of states,
number of positions, let's say, because that's
what this becomes.
It becomes for every bones.
I will have its position in character space,
and then I will have its velocity in character space.
So it's a bone count multiplied by two,
and x, y, z vector.
And I get a big matrix out of those.
And just to try to explain a little what you have now
because you have all those distance,
that you could start to compare all the distance between them while all the you
could compare the similarities of all the pose to each other and that's you
could start to think of that as a field that's basically what they would do
with a motion field so you could try to think of representing those differences
and that's what I would do here by just reducing the number of dimensions
because, you know, the dimensions I have now is, I don't remember how many bones I have, but it's
fairly big. And we're just telling, okay, try to see if there are similarities between all those
vectors and turn that into a 3D representation. And that's what the Yuma piloted me to do,
so we could have a kind of visualizations of the field. So what you have here, basically,
Every dot in this is one pose in the database, and you could see that the position they are
in space is the relations they have to each other, so probably all those around the move
in the same directions are in the same pose.
All the one here might be the jogging animations running forwards and that kind of stuff, so
one way of representing the motion field. It's just for helping. It has no true values on the
representation. It's just to be able to get your head around the fact that we build a motion field,
but it's a motion field in a really high dimension. So this one is just a projection of something
simpler to be able to visualize it. Now what we need is that for every pose that we will have
we need to be able to find which poses will be the closest to us. So what's the paper? Basically
what the paper is doing. So that's the similarity weight. That's how you compute the similarity
weight, my functions over there. And then when we will try to make an animation for those we need
to be able to find the nearest neighbor of our pose. So I will be in one pose with certain velocities
and I want to find the 15 pose that are closest to me. They do an approximative
nearest neighbor. I'll be lazy in my case because I don't have a lot of animations.
So what I would do is that I would just drop the entire matrix here in PyTorch and I would
just do a true search using the GPU. So basically I have a function that's allowed me to get,
you give him one vector and you ask him to return the k closest one.
And it runs on the GPU, so it can do it fairly quickly.
And the advantage of doing it in this way
is that I can query one vector, but I can also
query a batch at one point and request
to compute that for x number of vectors at the same time,
which would be nd a bit later.
Now, it's all good.
we have a database that is composed of all of our frames, we are able to find all the frames
that are the closest to us. How do we actually make an animation out of it? And that's how
you have the integration functions. And what the integration function does is this one,
it takes a state in which you are and it takes x number of action. And the actions is basically
the, in this case, the 15 different frames I will have found. And what you do is that you average
all the velocities of all the states you have with all the with the correct
weights and the weights come from you know the weights similarity weights. So you
average all the velocities and then you add those velocities to your state, to
your pose. So you're not adding the pose together you're only integrating the
velocities and you move your character towards that mixed velocities and then the reason why we
had that Y and remember the next frame is because now we need to compute the future velocities and
that we do the same. We take the the average of the future's velocities that becomes our velocity.
So, I will get the function to find key neighbors and the function to compute the new states
and I will come back to it because there is a little trick to do it after.
And what we have is this.
We have our character, I'll put it on spot so it doesn't go away, come back here.
it does, it basically wanders around the motion field. So for every pose, it finds the 15 closest
pose, compute the similarity weights and blend all those weights for the velocities and add that
velocity back to this one. If you do this, only this, what would happen is basically this. We
would move through the velocity field to the motion field, and at some point, hopefully we
we do it at some point. He might start to drift outside of the known data because
nothing forces him to stay in the motion field. You know, all the velocities have different weights
and I would love him to start to drift. That would be great. Let me force him back
from the beginning and hopefully I can get him to drift.
And so you see it starts to drift outside of the motion field because it probably reaches
points where they had no data in the field and the velocity pushed him outside of known velocities
and it starts to blend stuff together that really are not meant to be blend together.
What we do to fix this is that we will tag him with a small ratio saying okay you could blend
all the velocities you have. It's all fine but you will always add back 10% of the closest pose
you were to so basically you let him walk through the motion field but you always tug him towards
in the rear when you know that there is data and that's what the little 10 percent forces him to
go back into space of the motion field where there is actual data and then we could just to
represented. I would slow it down fairly. That does not work anymore. That was Y.
On the spot plot. And then you could display where all those frames of animations are inside of
the, oh that's me, that's because of me, where all those frame of dimensions are inside of the
motion field. So you could see where I am and why all the pose it picked and how much it blends
them. So that's a representation of what the motion field is, but as I said it's just a representation,
don't focus on this one too much, it's just to have an idea of what the field does and how it works.
And so, see that that ratio we have here is basically what was written here on how to compute
this. You actually have to compute the next frame and then compute how from where you are,
how you will what you will be needed to do to reach the frame you know and that's
give you one of the velocities and you integrate all those velocities back in.
So and that's what I'm doing here while computing the velocities to reach a
specific state and then computing the new states basically take the frames take take
the current frame, take all the indices
for all the next velocities, the weights,
and then you compute the velocities that
will allow you to go back in the known frames.
You blend all of that together, and that
give you the new pose.
And so that's how you could walk through the motion field.
Now, walking through the motion field itself
has no true interest except to make a character
walking definitely like that.
What you will want to do now is to be able to control this.
So being able to take our pad and make sure that we can move.
And the way we will do this is basically by saying,
okay, I've picked 15 different states that I can play.
that I can play. I have a similarity weight to know how to blend them. But if I want to get
control, what I could do is that I can give more importance to one of those states. And that's
what we will do. We compute the similarity weights for all the frames as we did before.
and then we replace the value of that similarity weights by so that's all
normalized but then we replace the value by a one for the action we want to pick
and then we renormalize so basically if I go here right now I'll let him do
whatever he wants but I could say now actually I want to play that one that
one is more important for me but then this one is more important and so on and
and so on. And you can see that the only thing I do is I replace the known value by a one
and I renormalize the entire weight. So I tell you to tug a bit more the direction
which of the 15 posts you want to pick, but not by forcing it too much. It's still using
the similarity weights to blend all of those together and then what we will have is this.
So the only thing I would do here is that I try to make the character walk
in the directions I want him to walk. So I will have a function that giving two different vectors,
it returns me the signed angle distance. I know the angle and I know the direction and the angle
compared to where I want to go. So that's what this function does. And my reward function
for my system would just be that it has the desired direction I want to walk towards.
it gets my current state and my next states. I'm not even using the current
states to be honest. And I'm just checking if basically the velocities of my
next states will lead me towards the orientation I want to use. So I would get
the difference between the orientation and my desired direction and the reward
is just a negative of the minus abstract. So the reward is more the penalty. If you're walking
exactly in the direction I want you to walk you get a score of zero and as soon as you deviate
you get a negative reward and that negativity is bigger if the bigger the error is.
and so I get my my pad and what you do is so the same thing you take the 15
possible weights you treat them as different actions compute the different
weights for them compute the next states it will give you and then compute the
reward for it and store that reward and then you pick pick the best one that's
That's it.
So I'll put him on spot also, otherwise he'll start to run.
So what you could see now, you get the directions.
And in green, you get the one he picked
as being the best action he could choose.
And I can start to control and see if I can walk
in a specific direction.
It might see here, for instance, a stack in the 15 pose
that forces him to keep running and turning.
might be able to solve that at some point,
but it has the greedy algorithm.
Sometimes it can turn fairly quickly,
but it gets stuck and doesn't manage to leave that way.
It states, yeah, I managed to make it turn
in the opposite way.
So greedy algorithm kind of work,
but of course we know it's far from being the optimal way
of picking your next frame of animation.
So we need to be able to use value functions
and Bellman equation to go to the next system.
So we'll use the Markov decision process control.
And what we really have in this case,
here with the reinforcement learning part
is that we basically have,
We have a continuous state space,
because my character here can truly be in any position.
So that's a continuous state space.
And what we have is also,
because we are on that field,
we have a continuous value function also.
So, we need to find a way to store that value function and what we will be doing in this
case is using what we already have.
We already have the motion field.
So, basically, what happens is that we have, inside of that field, we have the states that
all the frames we know. And then we will compute the value functions for each of those states.
So we get the value functions per one value function per goal, of course. So that one will be
discretized, but we will blend them together, but it will be discretized in a number of buckets
for all the directions we want to cover, let's say. And then we will compute those values for
every state in our motion field and then when we want to request the value for
that motion field we will for the value functions we will also use the motion
field to returns a blended values so if you request that's what they've done
here. You get the next states, the three you have here maybe, and then you will ask the motion
field itself again to find all the closest value and then to blend them back to give you the value
functions again. And so it means that what we've done to find the closest pose and blend all the
values with a similarity weight will be reused to also compute the value functions itself.
The value functions we will query at a certain state. We'll find the 15 closest values to that one
and then we will use the similarity weights to blend all the values functions that we had
into one value functions. And for the training of that value function,
what we'll do is that we will do fit value iteration. Why? Because we only work on the
states we know. So what will happen is that we will compute the next states of every
states we have and that's it we'll stop there we don't do explorations and all
like I said like like we were doing in other papers before we pre-compute all
the states and all the next states and all the actions we can take and we
compute the score and then we iterate through that until we have the
value functions that converge so what I would do is that I will pre-compute
first for all of my states the the 15 actions they can pick and and where for
those 15 actions I will compute also what if what happened if I picked action
one action two action three action four and so on and I will compute the position
position positions where those 15 will be and from those I will compute the
15 closest states that can be used to compute the value functions so that's
why you pre-compute this is because for every for every action you pick now you
you take the 15 closest poses you blend towards those 15 poses and for those
15s you retake 15 times the closest values so we will pre-compute this to
win sometimes and I will even I will just store it because it takes me 10
minutes to compute all of those and now that I have all those states you know I
have to have everything from here to the next frame and all the stuff I can
blend, I can start to compute the value functions. And I would do it with PyTorch, because, you
know, everything is pre-computed, it's one big buffer, everything can be done in parallel.
So let's do that on the GPU, so I can win a lot of time there computing that value functions.
And how I would do this is basically, I have my value functions that just a bunch of zeros to
start with. I'll put to the on the GPU my deltas of how much each of my frames will rotate.
I get the indices of the next frame to look at the the value functions and I get the weights.
I can compute in one go the offset of orientations that would happen for all of my states at once.
Yeah, I have a bunch of walking animations and a bunch of jogging animations, so I just have a flag
to know if I'm walking or jogging. And then you compute what will be the next orientations
for all the states for each actions and for each offsets in which I wanted to look at.
E compute the rewards and basically the reward is the same as before as the negativity of the
absolute next orientation and I'm also adding a score depending if I'm walking or jogging
because I only want to have one value function that makes me walking and one value function
that will make me jog. And then basically that's where the blending happens. So
how to say, you get a 2D blending in this case. What happens is that you first you will blend
the 15 values, you have to blend them with the weights. And then the orientations in what you
want to work. I've said that I've split the values in X numbers. And then you will just say, okay,
if my value is here right in the middle, I just need to do a linear blend between those two values.
And so that's what this part is doing. It is checking where you're landing in the orientation
and you just give you the range of the two values you have to blend and which blend factor
you have to blend them. So that's what this is computing. All of that is pre-computed once
into one find a bunch of big buffers and then at every iterations now every epoch you basically
take all the the the next value functions you gather we're using all those indices all the
values together you blend them you compute the next one and then you get the usual value functions
you know your Q is the reward plus the expected next reward and your best value is the maximum
of all the possible functions you have. Then I compute the Bellman residual to see
how much the current value functions compare to the expected value functions is
And that's how you to see if you are actually converging.
And then when you finish, I put that back on the CPU and I compute that twice.
So I will have two value functions.
I got a value functions for the walking and one value function for the jogging.
So basically, that's what this score will be.
It will be, it will give you an advantage of walking when asked you to walk and an advantage
of jogging when asked you to jog.
compute those two so I get 308 epoch to try to get that stabilized and I get the gamma of 0.99
and we could see now the convergence of the on the jogging one so that's the amount of difference
I had in the value functions and the expected next values.
And so what you have now with this value function is basically that.
We could start to use it as we use it usually.
So what I have is I only have one button to decide if I want to use the value functions
for walking or the value functions for jogging.
I got the direction in which I want to walk I compute my 15 closest neighbors
again then for all of them I compute the next pose and what I would do is that I
will store the query inside of what I call a batch query because I will store
for the 15 of them, I will store the positions where that would lead me and I
will store the batch data prime also so how much basically score that will give
me and then I can re-request the next indices and next weights but for the
batch now. That's why I said it was useful in PyTorch to be able to say I want to query
the system for one query or I can query it for a batch of queries. This is what's allowed
me to query the 15 different positions at once. And once you have this, what I could
do now is compute the future reward for each of those 15 different poses and I get the future reward
and then I use that future reward to know which one of the value I want to use.
Then I also use the contact of my foot and I've been lazy in this one, I only checking if the
toes are in contact or not and if they are in contact I lock them in positions and if they're not
I'll let them go and blend them back to their default positions for the animation slowly
that's it and I don't know anything more fancy on the the foot contact and so on
And that gives you this, the motion field.
So I will not put them on spot this time.
Given some room and here we go.
Now to be honest, I had to cheat and slow down a lot
the rendering and to speed it up again in a post.
And that's only because I guess it's my PyTorch
PyTorch implementations, calling PyTorch twice a frame probably forces the entire system
to go to synchronize the CPU and GPU and drop my frame rates pretty badly.
So this is speeded up and that's only speeded up because of my PyTorch implementations.
was the motion field and as I said is one of my favorite paper always wanted to implement that one
finally had the chance to look at it which was really great I hope you liked it and see you next time